Guide to the Erik Barnouw Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Erik Barnouw Papers
1920-1990.
Barnouw, Erik, 1908-2001.
21 linear ft. (ca.2,200 items in 46 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079647
History
Professor of Dramatic Arts at Columbia University, author, and editor.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, scripts, manuscripts, and reports regarding his activities in the American radio and film industries. Included are papers regarding projects for the United State Government, the Indian film industry, various television and radio networks, and private ventures. Also included is material regarding the Center for Mass Communications of Columbia University, in which Barnouw figured prominently and files for the books he has written.
Arrangement
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged. Box 1-1A: Cataloged correspondence; Boxes 1B-29: 1974 gift; Box 30: 1979 gift; Box 31-37: 1984 gift; Box 38: 1985 & 1992 gifts; Boxes 39-40: 1993 gift; Boxes 41-46 Addition (Unprocessed).
Subjects
Columbia University.--Press.--Center for Mass Communication.; Albert, Eddie.; Alperovitz, Gar.; Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973.; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884-1981.; Bergman, Ingrid, 1915-1982.; Bernays, Edward L., 1891-1995.; Bertelli, Gian Carlo.; Braudy, Leo.; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973.; Chayefsky, Paddy, 1923-1981.; Cooney, Joan Ganz.; Corwin, Norman, 1910-; Denison, Merrill, 1893-1975.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980.; Flaherty, Frances Hubbard.; Flaherty, Robert Joseph, 1884-1951.; Fontanne, Lynn.; Friendley, Fred W.; Graff, Henry F. (Henry Franklin), 1921-; Horgan, Paul, 1903-1995.; Iwasaki, Akira, 1903-; Jessup, Philip C. (Philip Caryl), 1897-1986.; Kagan, Norman.; Krishnaswamy, Subranmanyam.; Laflin, Louis Ellsworth, 1898-; Lasker, Mary.; Leyda, Jay, 1910-1988.; Lorenz, Pare.; Lurtsema, Robert J.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Malamud, Bernard.; Manvell, Roger, 1909-1987.; Mareth, Paul D.; Medina, Harold R. (Harold Raymond), 1888-1990.; Mekas, Jonas, 1922-; Merriam, Eve, 1916-1992.; Merton, Robert King, 1910-2003.; Nash, Ogden, 1902-1971.; Olivier, Laurence, 1907-1989.; Postman, Neil.; Ray, Satyajit, 1921-1992.; Riefenstahl, Leni.; Robeson, Eslanda Goode, 1896-1965.; Roud, Richard.; Rubbo, Michael.; Solomon, Rosalind.; Stirling, Nora B., 1900-; Stone, Idella Purnell, 1901-; Suid, Lawrence H.; Swing, Raymond, 1887-1968.; Thant, U, 1909-1974.; Thapar, Raj.; Thapar, Romesh.; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-1989.; Van Dyke, Willard.; Wilkins, Roy, 1901-1981.; Wright, Basil.; Motion picture industry--India.; Motion picture industry--United States.; Documentary films.; Radio.; Television.; Articles.; Interviews.; Lectures.; Proofs.; Scripts.; Authors.; College teachers.; Editors.; Professors.
Acquisition
04/08/74 M-74-04-08 Barnouw, Erik Gift
11/04/92 M-92-11-04 Papers Barnouw, Erik Gift
M-93-01-28 Papers Barnouw, Erik Gift
Alternate Formats
Peal S. Buck's letter is also available on microfilm.
W.H. Auden letters are also available on microfilm.
Gift of Erik Barnouw, 1974, 1979, 1984, 1985, 1992, & 1993.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 1B, 2-46. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Finding aid in repository.
- Series I. Cataloged Correspondence
  - Albert, Eddie (Box 1)
  - Alperovitz, Gar (Box 1)
  - Auden, W. H. (Box 1)
    (Correspondence is also available on microfilm# 91-2095)
  - Baldwin, Roger N. (Box 1)
  - Bergman, Ingrid (Box 1)
  - Bernays, Edward L. (Box 1)
  - Bertelli, Gian Carlo (Box 1)
  - Braudy, Leo (Box 1)
  - Buck, Pearl S. (Box 1)
    (Correspondence is also available on microfilm# 91-2094-2)
  - Chayefsky, Paddy (Box 1)
  - Cooney, Joan Ganz (Box 1)
  - Corwin, Norman (Box 1)
  - Denison, Merrill (Box 1)
  - Douglas, William 0. (Box 1)
  - Flaherty, Frances H (Box 1)
  - Fontanne, Lynne (Box 1)
  - Friendley, Fred W. (Box 1)
  - Graff, Henry F. (Box 1)
  - Horgan, Paul (Box 1)
  - Hughes, Harcher (Box 1)
  - Iwasaki, Akira (Box 1A)
  - Jessup, Philip C. (Box 1A)
  - Kagan, Norman (Box 1A)
  - Kirkus, Virginia (Box 1A)
  - Krishnaswamy, S. (Box 1A)
  - Laflin, Louis E. (Box 1A)
  - Lasker, Mary (Box 1A)
  - Leyda, Jay (Box 1A)
  - Lorentz, Pare (Box 1A)
  - Lurtsema, Robert J. (Box 1A)
  - MacLeish, Archibald (Box 1A)
  - Malamud, Bernard (Box 1A)
  - Manvell, Roger (Box 1A)
  - Mareth, Paul D. (Box 1A)
  - Medina, Harold R. (Box 1A)
  - Mekas, Jonas (Box 1A)
  - Merriam, Eve (Box 1A)
  - Merton, Robert (Box 1A)
  - Nash, Ogden (Box 1A)
  - Olivier, Laurence (Box 1A)
  - Postman, Neil (Box 1A)
  - Ray, Satyajit (Box 1A)
  - Riefenstahl, Leni (Box 1A)
  - Robeson, Eslands G. (Box 1A)
  - Roud, Rlchard (Box 1A)
  - Rubbo, Michael (Box 1A)
  - Shaw, Sir Run Run (Box 1A)
  - Solomon, Rosalind (Box 1A)
  - Stirling, Nora B. (Box 1A)
  - Stone, Idella P. (Box 1A)
  - Suid, Lawrence H. (Box 1A)
  - Swing, Raymond (Box 1A)
  - Thant, U (Box 1A)
  - Thapar, Romesh & Raj (Box 1A)
  - Thomson, Virgil (Box 1A)
  - Turteltaub, Saul (Box 1A)
  - Van Dyke, Willard (Box 1A)
  - Wilkins, Roy (Box 1A)
  - Wright, Basil (Box 1A)
- Series II. 1974 Gift
  - U.S. War Department Materials (Box 1B)
  - Indian Film Industry (Box 1B)
  - Constitutional Law Series (NET) (Box 2-5)
  - Theatre Guild Scripts (radio and television) (Box 6-9)
    (Theatre Guild on the Air, radio, sponsored by U.S. Steel U.S. Steel Hour, television, produced by Theatre Guild)
  - Public Health and Welfare Projects (Box 10-11)
  - Radio scripts, 1920-1950 (Box 12)
  - Radio Commentaries (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Scripts (Box 13)
  - "American Radio: 1927 A Research Study of One Year of Radio" (Box 13)
  - Representative television scripts by various writers, 1940-present (Box 14-16)
  - Documentary film scripts and related material from various countries (Box 17-18)
  - Manuscripts and related correspondence regarding Barnouw's three volume work, History of Broadcasting in the United States (Box 19-21)
  - Scripts (radio, television, and film) by Barnouw, 1930-1960s (Box 22-25)
  - Center for Mass Communication, Columbia University--Related Materials (Box 22-25)
  - Books Inscribed to Barnouw (Box 26)
  - Documentary: A History of the Non-Fiction Film--Typescript (Box 27)
  - Tube of Plenty--Typescript and Proofs (Box 28-29)
- Series III. 1979 Gift
  - Hiroshima-Nagasaki 1945--Correspondence and material related to the film (Box 30)
- Series III. 1984 Gift
  - Documentary: A History of the Non-Fiction Film (Oxford University Press, 1984)--Correspondence and other related materials, 1970-1983 (Box 31)
  - Handbook of radio production (Little, Brown & Co., 1949). (Box 32)
  - Handbook of radio writing (Little, Brown & Co., 1939)--Correspondence & other related materials, 1939-1959 (Box 32)
  - A History of Broadcasting in the United States (Oxford University Press): A tower in Babel (1966); The golden web (1968); and The image empire (1970)-- Correspondence & other related materials, 1939-1983 (Box 32)
  - Indian Film, Revised edition by E. Barnouw & S. Krishnaswamy (Columbia University Press, 1980)--Correspondence, Manuscripts, proofs, & other related materials, 1977-1982. (Box 33)
  - Lectures, articles, & interviews, 1976-1980 (Box 34)
  - Library of Congress: Chief of Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division & Various Consultancies--Correspondence & other related materials, 1975-1983 (Box 34)
  - The Magician and the Cinema (Oxford University Press, 198l)--Correspondence, manuscript, proofs, & other related materials, 1977-1983 (Box 35)
  - National Educational Television. "Mr. Secretary" & other proposals. Correspondence, scripts, & other related materials, 1958-1963. (Box 35)
  - "Problems of Democracy" (.Center for Mass Communications). Correspondence, scripts, & other related materials, 1960-1961 (Box 36)
  - Radio Scripts--Correspondence & scripts, 1935-1951 (Box 36)
  - Robert Flaherty Film Seminar (1982)--Correspondence & other related materials, 1981-1982 (Box 36)
  - The Sponsor (Oxford University Press, 1978)
    - Correspondence & Other related materials, 1974-1977 (Box 36)
    - Correspondence, manuscripts, proofs, & other related materials, 1977-1979 (Box 37)
- Series V. 1985 and 1992 Gifts
  - Subseries V.1. 1985 Gift
    - Radio drama in action. (Farrar & Rinehart, 1945) (Box 38)
      ("Includes revealing autobiographical notes by a number of different writers, most of whom were little known at the time, Manv later became celebrated in other media, but were, in the early 1940s mainly concerned with radio...Other contributors to the anthology were writers prominent in other media but occasionally drawn to radio, especially during World War II...The anthology was reprinted several times, remaining in print until the late 1950s and widely used in College and university courses."- Erik Barnouw)
      These are photocopies of original manuscripts held by the State Historical Society of Wisconsin.
  - General correspondence, 1942, 1944 (Box 38)
  - Farrar & Rinehart, publishers, 1945-1947 (Box 38)
  - Foreign editions, royalties, 1947 (Box 38)
  - Benet, Stephen Vincent (Box 38)
  - Buck, Pearl S. (Box 38)
  - Chevigny, Hector (Box 38)
  - Corwin, Norman (Box 38)
  - Dryer, Bernard (Box 38)
  - Gottlieb, Joseph (Box 38)
  - Hughes, Langston (Box 38)
  - Kleiner, Harry (Box 38)
  - Lampell, Mi Hard (Box 38)
  - Laurents, Arthur (Box 38)
  - Lawrence, Jimmy (Box 38)
  - Lomax, Alan (Box 38)
  - Lyon, Peter (Box 38)
  - MacDougall, Ranald (Box 38)
  - Marquis, Arnold (Box 38)
  - Michael, Sandra (Box 38)
  - Miller, Arthur (Box 38)
  - Mulvey, Timothy (Father) (Box 38)
  - Oboler, Arch (Box 38)
  - Ottley, Roi (Box 38)
  - Robson, William (Box 38)
  - Rosten, Norman (Box 38)
  - Welles, Orson (Box 38)
  - Wishengrad, Morton (Box 38)
  - Miscellaneous: Playwrights whose works were omitted. Also, one copy of the printed book. (Box 38)
- Subseries V.2. 1992 Gift
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and documents, 1927-1989 (Box 38)
- Series VI. 1993 Gift
  - International Encyclopedia of Communications
    (Per E. Barnouw, these files "are from my personal files as editor-in-chief of the encyclopedia. The official files are at the Annenberg School of Communications, University of Pennsylvania. The 4-vol encyclopedia was published by Oxford University Press in 1989.")
    - Genesis and funding of the project, 1982-83 (Box 39)
    - Organization, contracts, progress report, 1983-84 (Box 39)
    - Editorial correspondence, 1985-88 (Box 39)
  - Hiroshima-Nagasaki 1945 (Box 39)
    (Per E. Barnouw, "Supplementing the original Hiroshima-Nagasaki file, this file records continuing reactions to the film, 1973-88; the evolution of various articles about the film in journals; and of the video The Case of the A-Bomb Footage.")
  - Fable Safe--File on the evolution and history of this controversial film on the arms race, 1972-1989 (Box 40)
  - US-USSR Projects (Box 40)
    (Organization and history of (a) the 1989 Glasnost Film Festival tour of USA; (b) the 1990 Flaherty Film Seminar in Riga, Latvia, and follow-up visits to USSR documentary studios; and (c) the 1990 USSR tour of the American Showcase (d) Documents supplementing these, including the final Showcase report)
  - Tube of Plenty, 1971-1986 (Box 40)
    (Evolution of the one-volume condensation and updating of the 3-volume History of Broadcasting in the United States (A Tower in Babel, The Golden Web, and The Image Empire).)